I've personally grown my social media over
3.65 million subscribers, followers,
whatever you want to call it.
And up until about a year and a half ago,
I did all
the editing myself.
Easily over 4,000 Reels, maybe 250
YouTube videos.
I edited every single podcast episode
that I've ever done.
That's one of the reasons I stopped the
podcast, was it was literally me carrying
around in a duffel bag two cameras,
microphones, broadcaster mix deck.
And with nearly 13 million downloads,
I thought, you know what?
Now I'm probably in a position to bring it
back.
In this video,
I'm going to teach you how to edit
potentially with less effort, get
better results, jump into the new era,
new way of getting attention
online, save yourself time,
and give you a glimpse into exactly how I
do it.
The first thing we need to look at
is the golden rules of content creation
and
editing. If your video is 90 seconds
or less, don't script it.
Just have a generalized idea about what
you're going to talk about and talk about
it. Now, if your video is over 90 seconds,
I recommend you make some notes.
For me,
I only ever do one page with a can of
Nutonic just to make sure I
don't miss anything,
because it's very annoying
when you get into the edit and you
miss something. Now,
these nine rules we're about to go into,
I had
to instill into young Declan. Declan,
as you're editing this, why not show the
world yourself with a thumbs up at your
desk? The first 30 seconds.
If you're going to use B-roll or overlay,
do it early.
And to show you why,
let's head over to my big YouTube for a
second.
One of the most popular videos I've ever
done.
Let's look into this one,
"The Downfall of Modern Podcasts." You'll
notice that
straight away, because this
was talking about podcasts,
I thought I'd establish
one scene, two scenes, three scenes,
four scenes, five scenes, six
scenes. So in the first six seconds,
including myself, we've now had eight
scenes. Me, scene one, two, three, four,
five, six, and then back to me.
Then in the introduction,
you realize the headphones aren't even
connected.
And then better yet, neither
is the microphone,
and we start getting into the
video. Now,
this is quite literally point and shoot.
Here,
I was telling off Etienne because he still
had the camera pointed at me at
the desk. I was like, "Come on,
bro." Actually, that was genuinely a moan.
Now, this got over a million views,
3,200 comments, and I
just got Etienne to come follow me around.
There was no planning.
There was no strategizing.
A little bit of B-roll.
Went down to the whiteboard, and honestly,
I made all of this up.
It was actually a conversation
that I'd had earlier that day, which
is going to be
rule number one, section B.
Content ideation should be conversations
that you're
having with people. So if you're a physio,
one of your clients might say, "Why is
it that this tendonitis aches so much?"
And you might say, "Oh, it's because it's
inflamed." And your client goes,
"What's inflammation?" You should go
[gasps] ,
"If my client's asking what inflammation
is, maybe the whole world will want to
know." You could be an accountant.
Your client goes,
" [gasps] Because it's nearly the
financial year, should I spend
loads of money so
that I don't have to pay it in corp tax?"
You go, "No, that's not
how it works.
Just because you spend it doesn't mean
the..." Whatever.
You could be a content creator where
someone says to you,
"How much do I need to
edit my content?" You go, "Oh,
do you know what?
Let me make you a video."
And I just rifted for ages on this video
about getting
crushed. It was just a rant.
13,000 subscribers, nearly three
Gs. Probably time I changed the title
and thumbnail. Shut up. Go away.
So if you're going to put some effort into
putting overlay and B-roll, get it in
there early,
which brings us on to stage number two.
The first part of the edit
is the most important. So important.
Probably 20 times more important than
anything that comes later.
I'll explain why.
A first date.
When you meet someone for a first date,
you take more care than ever
into what you're wearing,
what shoes you wear,
what aftershave you're wearing, how
your hair looks,
because you know there's no point putting
too much effort into a
second, third, or fourth date because
if the first one doesn't go right,
there is
no second date.
So your first minute of content must
follow the same rules.
Think of it this way.
If you're doing a 10-minute video
and you're going to
allocate 10 hours of editing,
it's very easy for people to think, "Oh,
one hour
per minute." No, no, no.
It's quite all right to put two
or three hours into that
first 30 to 45 seconds. The same way
that if you're going to allocate half an
hour into a Reel to edit,
which it shouldn't take too much longer
than that, maybe
10 minutes goes into the first 15 seconds,
and then the rest of the time goes into
the rest. Because if you do not nail
that imperative part of it, people
will leave.
Let's show you my other YouTube account.
Let's find my best performing video
recently.
This one, which don't worry,
I'll put a link to at the end of this one.
If we go down to the retention graph,
even this banger video, that has
made me nearly 11 grand,
not to mention thousands, well,
1,500 leads. Oh, look. Yeah, $10,500.
Most people are gone by halfway.
Two-thirds of people have gone.
Over two-thirds of people have gone.
So there's no point in me saving my
amazing call to action or the best edit
or the
best part of the story till later because
most people have gone, brother.
Even this video right now,
most people have gone.
And I probably should have put more effort
into the introduction thinking about it
like that. Which means
that your call to actions have to come
earlier.
For instance, Short-Form Content Mastery,
99 US dollars.
There's going to be a link in the
description to this video.
I could have told you that later on,
but I'll tell you now.
If you want to get better at making
content, just give me £75
and I'll teach you.
So we move on to the very next rule.
Should you script videos or not script?
There are some teleprompters over there
behind the Porsche. Flex.
You can get teleprompters
that you put an iPad in.
There's software for your iPad,
and you can press a button.
There's teleprompters you put your phone
into, press buttons.
There's the Elgato prompter, which
is very good,
which works as an extension of a
monitor.
This is what I teach people in my
mentorship.
Go make 50 videos with a teleprompter.
Go make 50 videos without.
Which ones perform better?
You now know whether
or not you should be reading from a
teleprompter. Me,
I like to rift because even now,
there's only, what,
100 words planning this video because I
know what I'm talking about.
I do this all day,
every day inside of Discord.
I do not need to script it, brother.
So figure out what style works for you
because some people just sound a bit
robotic
on a teleprompter,
but other people sound amazing.
So find a style that works for you. Also,
some people just like to make
sure that every single word
is written out, and other people are like,
"Yeah,
whatever." Which brings me on to the next
rule.
If you watch almost all of my content,
it doesn't have music
in. And if it does have any music in,
it will be because Declan put it in
there,
and Declan will put it in there without me
telling him to.
Declan, give people another thumbs up
if you want. I'll tell you a quick story.
I used to have a videographer called
Etienne.
Etienne He won't mind me saying he
was a bit
retarded. Now, I had to sack Etienne.
No, that's not code name for Lucas,
although he did get sacked as well.
There were
many stories where Etienne made mistakes.
Quick tangent on that story,
which you wouldn't have had
if we'd done this in the
teleprompter. I always thought
that in French, je ne sais quoi meant
something kind of special,
something unique.
That lady just had a little bit of je ne
sais quoi. I'm in Dubai with Etienne.
We're filming some content.
I'm in the car, I go,
"Oi." Because Etienne was French,
French Canadian,
which could be the worst form of French.
Anyway, I went, "Oi, Etienne,
what does je ne sais quoi mean?" Je ne
sais quoi.
He goes, "I do not know." I went, "Bruv,
you're French Canadian.
Je ne sais quoi,
what does it mean?" He goes,
"I don't know." I went, "This guy's a
fucking retard. Etienne,
how do you not understand what je ne sais
quoi means?" He
goes, "Bro,
it means I do not know." So it turns out
for years, maybe I'm the
retard. I've been saying to people,
"Oh yeah,
that girl you went on a date with,
sounds like she had a bit of je ne sais
quoi." Anyway, back to the story as to why
Etienne got fired. There
were many reasons, but one of which,
imagine I said to him, "Hey bro,
could we get the edit back by 5:00 PM
tonight?
I'm going out for dinner with my friends."
He goes, "Sure, no problem." Anyway, he
goes, "Bro, it's uploading." I'm sweet.
I'm sat by my desk.
I'm thinking I'm going to watch the video,
sign it off, post it, amazing.
Go for dinner. Great. "Hey mate,
how's the video?" "Yeah,
just uploading." I'm
like, "Mate, what are you uploading on,
a 3G SIM card?" Anyway, so he's uploading
it.
Finally it comes through.
I go to proof it, space bar,
three seconds in,
hate the music. Hate it. I went, "Brother,
this music is the worst
backing music ever that I've heard.
I didn't tell you to put this in.
Why'd you put it in?" He goes, "Yeah,
I thought it gives them effect." I went,
"No
bro, I hate it." I said, "Bro,
send me a version without the music in."
He goes,
"Okay,
it's going to take 37 minutes to upload."
I went,
"Etienne, brother, 37 minutes?
I've just been sat here for
37 minutes waiting for this 10.4 gigabyte
file to upload.
Now I've got to wait another 37 minutes.
I've got to leave for dinner in 10." So
because of that,
I couldn't proof the video
before I went for dinner. I go for dinner,
I come home. I'm with my missus.
I'm just not going to sit at my desk
and proof a video at 11:00, 12:00 PM.
So I've lost 24 hours.
That video could've been up,
could've been generating leads,
getting interest, blah, blah, blah.
We might as well have filmed
and done it all a day later.
I might as well have said, "Hey bro,
have the afternoon off,
because I don't know,
je ne sais quoi.
You're a retard." So little things like
that.
Music more all too often can ruin a video
than it can
benefit it. Now, sure, for dramatic scene,
pretty much those of
you that use music in videos
and you know how to do it because you
learn
professionally, you can use it.
But everyone else
that kind of thinks it's cool,
stop doing it.
Because every time I put these on
and I critique your reels, your
music's too loud. And
if your music's too loud
and I can't hear what you're saying,
I'm gone, brother. Everyone
is looking for a reason to leave.
People do not like you
when they do not know you.
And you choosing shitty music
or bad music or music
that doesn't go with the
video,
you're giving them an opportunity to
leave.
Which brings us on to the next point.
We have hooks and we have introductions.
Hooks and introductions.
In a real short-form content,
we must use a hook.
We can use a statement hook. This
is the best way for you to save money on
long-haul flights.
We have a question hook.
Have you heard about the world's first
productivity drink called Nootonic?
We can have a preview hook where we show
things that are to come.
There are many ways to have hooks,
but ultimately in the first five seconds,
people
want to know what the video is about,
how it's going to benefit them,
and whether
or not they should watch it. Now,
when it comes to an introduction on
YouTube, the
reason that you choose the title
and thumbnail first,
and you'll even notice on
this document that I've got the title
here, and then an idea of the
thumbnail,
is the very first thing I need to say in
this content
has to pay off the title and thumbnail.
Because some people
are just previewing it,
some people have just clicked it.
And when we looked at the retention graph
before, so many people are looking
for a reason to leave.
And it's often because they've started
watching the
video, they've heard the hook,
the start of the setup, and they go,
"This ain't for
me." Cool. But some people stayed.
So it's imperative
that you identify the difference between
the two.
In a long-form video,
you need to pay off the packaging that
was used to get
people to click. And in short form,
we need a hook.
Which actually, Declan,
later on in this video,
I'm going to be editing some
content. So maybe we take some of that
and put it near the beginning just for a
bit
of overlay and B-roll. Look at this, guys.
We are putting the formula into fucking
action in the middle of the edit.
Keep that in there, Declan, if you want.
Which brings me on to the next one.
Reference them early. Remember,
this video was not about me and how I
edit,
although I did use an appeal to authority
mentioning how many followers I
got. But everything here
is talking about your content,
about how you can blow up
your channels. So remember,
it's not how I lost four kilograms in six
weeks, it's
how you can lose four kilograms in six
weeks.
It's not how I managed to recover from ACL
surgery, it's how you can recover from
ACL surgery. Everything is about them.
Humans only care about themselves.
But James, what about philanthropists?
Yeah, give money to charity. Why?
Because of the starving kids in Africa?
No, to make themselves feel better.
My mind will not be changed on that.
Fuck, how good is some caffeine
and nootropics together? All right.
Cut anything that's not needed.
When you go through your video in your
edit, which
we're about to get into,
you need to chop fucking everything
that doesn't need to
be in there. Chop it up, get it out.
And again, in the beginning of your video,
if
you can chop the first five seconds of
your video and it still makes sense,
get rid
of it, brother.
Sometimes you get a nice steak,
but you've still got to trim the
fat.
Sometimes when I'm editing people's
content, their setup is better than the
hook. They're like, "Imagine if there
was a way to lose weight
that didn't mean you
had to be in a calorie deficit."
And they go, "This is four bananas
and this is
three croissants." And I'm like, "Whoa,
whoa, whoa, whoa.
That second thing you said, bro,
start with that because it sounds better.
Delete the first fucking ramble garbage
you said.
This is four bananas and this
is three croissants.
That's a setup,
but I think it makes a better hook than
your hook did." So again,
another golden rule,
you're always going to make better edits
on fucking desktop.
None of you all are going to be getting
that many millions of views doing an edit
on a fucking phone. Some of you do.
Sam Cornforth might, but you're
not fucking Sam Cornforth, all right?
Get it on desktop, have some fun with it.
And the last point,
really the main point in this entire
video, is not to over
fucking edit. So let's get into it,
brother.
Let's get into it.
I don't really edit much these days.
It's more of a Declan job.
It's not even to do with time, I'm
important. That's a joke. Relax.
It's a joke.
Calm down, brother. Cool.
I'm not even sure how DaVinci works all
that well, to be
honest, but Declan's the boss. Okay,
now I appreciate you're probably
not going to get much audio from this,
but maybe I'll just crank up the volume.
Actually, that might work better.
First things first,
we just have the playhead here,
and you can see these little
bars down here. This
is where we just want to crop into.
We just want to get to here
and use the shortcut to either chop,
make a
split And delete, or there
are other shortcuts you can do.
Oh, where's my bloody audio?
Let's have a little look at the
preferencinos.
Output device.
Let's go studio display speakers,
just to give a bit of
feedback to everyone. Lovely.
So the first things I need to do,
make sure there's some audio attached to
this.
Very good point.
Make sure you've got audio.
Every time you start recording, test that.
Make sure your mic is plugged in.
I often talk a little bit at the beginning
of an edit, just so I can see the audio
bars moving. Second thing
is to make sure that I'm in frame.
Make sure you're in frame.
Make sure you've got a preview.
That's why I like Sony FX3. Got
that little pop-out.
GH5II, Panasonic got the little pop-out.
And if you haven't got one of them,
you can get a little monitor
that goes to the
side, just to make sure
that you're in frame.
If not,
you can always get QuickTime up on your
computer and have a little look.
And you can even use that for your phone.
So those of you,
if you're recording on that camera, stop,
use that one.
You can plug it in with a USB C,
and you can go to QuickTime and see
yourself in it. Now,
it becomes a bit of a skill,
but you get your track head to
this point, and then boop.
Then I will often look away from the
camera, think about what I'm-
Yeah, I'm having a little think
about what I'm going to talk about. Here.
Boom
If you want to get more from-
Now, one thing I could spot here,
actually,
is you see my eye line's a little bit
low, brother. It's a little bit low.
Let's bring that inspector out.
So I'm going to take the whole clip.
I'm going to zoom in just a tiny bit.
What is going on here, brother?
I'm just going to zoom in a bit,
and I'm just going
to change the position. Just bring
that eye line up a tad.
Now, cropping in,
that's not going to ruin anyone's day.
It's not.
But, my days, that already looks better.
And these are the mistakes
that happen in content.
I went to say something
and then just gave up.
If you-
Then we get to this bit. Boom. Start
And that's typically what editing is like.
You just don't see the mistakes.
Boom. I'm in.
If you want to get more views from editing
less and putting less effort into
things, then it's imperative you do this.
Boom. We want to cut straight away.
Let myself breathe.
Let myself get my breath back.
Look around a little bit.
Then we're going to cut again.
I might even go look at my notes,
if I have notes, and then come back.
Yes.
Now we just want to sometimes just check
the sequence between the two.
You do this. You need to ensure
that you do-
Lovely.
Let me just go across to the next track
head.
You need to ensure-
You can see it's another mistake.
So we come across again.
We just get rid of that first bit.
You need to ensure that-
Then again,
we just double-check the sequence
Or that you do, you need to ensure-
And this bit was a repetition,
so we come back again
Into things,
then it's imperative you do this.
You need to ensure that you do this.
Cool. This is obviously me chatting shit.
You get that, but-
Don't overedit.
Cool. Now, you see where I said,
"Don't overedit?" I'm thinking, hmm,
that's quite
a poignant point. Is poignant French?
I don't know. Ask Etienne.
That you do this. Don't overedit.
So for this,
we can maybe even look for a little crop
to fill or whatever you want
to call it. So in essence,
we're just going to zoom in a little bit
further, but
you'll notice my eye line just drifted up
a bit.
So we're just going to bring
that eye line back to where it was,
and this will make
sense in a second. Then we can cut here.
Now watch this little segment.
Or that you do this. Don't overedit.
And then-
So there, already, you see
that little jump in. Wonderful.
Let's have a look as it flows now
You do this. Don't overedit. Crop in,
maybe, when I say
something like this.
I already said crop in.
It's like I knew this was coming.
So again,
rather than setting up another camera
or a B angle or
overcomplicating the edit,
sometimes I just feel it makes so much
more sense to
just crop in when you say something of
importance.
Now, the majority of all of my content,
there's no music, there's no
subtitles, fade. I'm just talking.
I'm using hand gestures,
and I'm just using sensible jump cuts,
where I can
go from one thing-
Otherwise, your edit will fail
And just get the point across. Now again,
if we go over to any of these
videos that I put out,
do you notice it's just talking.
Oh no, Miss Rachel, go away.
You'll notice it's just talking.
Sometimes I screen record at the same
time, like today, but it really is just
screen records and straight edits.
There doesn't need to be any amazing,
crazy editing to any of this.
Even with this video,
it's a bit of point and shoot.
Sometimes we just take some footage where
no one's talking and overlay it when
people are talking.
People just like to be able to look at
something while they
talk. But again, point and shoot.
Every single video that I shoot,
I would call a same day edit.
That's really the lesson I'm teaching
here.
If you can't put out a video the same day
that you filmed it, chances
are you're over-editing.
You watch MrBeast
and you watch these creators that
put far too much into content,
but they might need to,
but you just don't.
Everything you should shoot should be able
to be filmed, edited, chopped up
in a day.
And that's not just to give it to a
videographer.
I'm talking that's for you,
the majority of you, doing your own stuff.
Again here, in the onset,
got Declan to do some fancy animations
that probably
took him, I don't know, like an hour.
The reason I did that
is because there's no other animations in
the video.
We did use a B camera in this one.
We actually used a flipping
wide lens on this. It was his idea.
I don't think we're mad on it.
But even look at this one. This video
was just a live stream for an
hour, answering questions. No editing.
No editing at all.
And if we look at the flipping analytics
of that bad boy.
I'm on the wrong YouTube. Bear with.
Everyone out there can say you really need
to edit your content, and make
[mumbling] .
That is a year old live stream.
It's had 48 views in the last 48 hours.
That's still getting one view an hour,
which doesn't seem significant.
The average view duration
is 10 minutes 13 seconds.
That's longer than a TED Talk.
That was me just going live.
Just going live.
It's been 84 years.
Let's go to the big channel for a sec.
This video,
still getting two views an hour.
Again, just recorded the phone,
got Etienne to pass it to me.
We drove to the petrol station.
Absolutely zero planning.
Little bit of B-roll.
Got this out the same day. This
is MPIC video. Put it out the same day.
This was just me reacting to another video
I'd already done. Same day.
Not one video here. Look at this one.
The creatine gummy scandal video.
I came to the gym.
I think the recording and editing of
that took three hours.
Closing statement.
The majority of you need speed on your
side.
Sure, I need effort.
I'm not saying make shit videos for the
sake of it, but you
should be putting out a piece of content a
day.
And even those of you
that move to YouTube should probably try
and to be put out
same day posting content, because
if you have a video that does really well,
happy
days. If you have a video that bombs,
you're going to be a bit depressed.
Now, if a video bombs
and you only put one day into it, fine.
But some of you out there
are putting weeks and days
and even months into videos,
then they're bombing, and it
is ruining your relationship with content
creation,
which is a big fucking problem,
and it needs to stop.
So instead, you need to make sure you
are putting out same day edits on
every platform, whatever it is.
A short should not take more than half an
hour, 45
minutes.
A long should not take more than a day.
Then you can start churning out.
You quite literally need to put out
hundreds of videos.
For any of you out there
that feel brave enough,
you could go to posting on YouTube
every day. It sucks,
but you need to get the feedback from
things bombing so that
you can course correct
and make content properly.
Because some of you don't even know who
your audience is yet, and the only way you
can do that is putting out loads
and loads of content. Right.
Short-form content mastery.
There's a link in the description.
And if you're someone who identifies as
lazy, but you still want to make millions
and do really well in business, well,
I made this video for you.
It is quite literally the easiest way
and laziest way to market your business,
and
people are absolutely frothing it.
So jump in. Enjoy. Bye-bye.